<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached vpon the fifth of November, 1679 in the Cathedrall Church of Gloucester / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
            <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16199341</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16199341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1085:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached vpon the fifth of November, 1679 in the Cathedrall Church of Gloucester / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
                  <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Barksdale ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXII, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105057:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON PREACHED Vpon the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>In the Cathedrall Church at Glouceſter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CL. BARKSDALE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed for <hi>John Barksdale</hi> Book-ſeller in Ciceſter, 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105057:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105057:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. CXXII. VI.</bibl>
               <q>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem: They ſhall proſper that Love thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O obſerve the coherence and meaning of the Text, you may be pleaſed to look back to the 3 verſe, <hi>Jeruſalem is build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a City, that is Compact together: i. e.</hi> Jeruſalem is a Lovely place; the very buildings, being ſo uniform and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn'd together, are very beautifull; an Emblem of that unity of minds, that ſhould be in the Church of God. Then at the 4 verſe, <hi>Thither the Tribes go up, the Tribes of the Lord, unto the Testimony of Iſrael</hi> (or rather as our Critical Paraphraſt has it, <hi>according to the Commandment unto Iſrael) to give thanks unto the Name of the Lord.</hi> It was the place to which all the Inhabitants of the Land were obliged to go up thrice every year, to commemorate the mercies of God, afforded to his people Then at the 5 verſe, <hi>For there are ſet Thrones of Judgment, the Thrones of the Houſe of David:</hi> i. e. Beſides the Service of God, there alſo is the Sanhedrim, or ſupreme Judicatory of the Nation, that great Court, where the higheſt matters are decided. And there alſo is the Palace of David, where the King reſides and his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105057:3"/> Poſterity ſhall ſit upon his Throne. All theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations infer the Duty of the Text, <hi>Pray for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the City of God, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l compacted and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in it ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem is the place where the Houſe of God is, and his ſolemn ſervice: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eruſalem is the ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the King, and the ſeat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtice: Therfore <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> It is the du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Good men, to pray for this place, and to love it moſt affection<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly, and to beſeech God to beſtow a quiet enjoyment of all theſe Advantages, and all manner of proſperity upon it. <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee:</hi> They that love, and pray, and contribute their utmoſt to Jeruſalem, ſhall not looſe their reward, they ſhall gain to themſelves proſperitie.</p>
            <p>The Text you ſee, being thus explained, falls into two parts, <hi>A Duty, and a Reaſon:</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duty in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e former words, <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem:</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the later, <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee:</hi> a reaſon which is the great Reaſon, and Common Motive to duty, taken from their own intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and benefit: <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee,</hi> ô Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>So that, we have theſe two Obſervations:</p>
            <q>
               <p>I. It is our duty to pray for the peace of the Church and State wherin we live.</p>
               <p>II. They that well performe this duty, procure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and happineſs for themſelves.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I. It is our duty to love and pray for the peace of the Church and State wherin we live. I joyn the Church and the State together: for, as I ſaid, at Jeruſalem was the Houſe of God, the Temple; and there alſo was the Houſe of the King, and the Court of Juſtice. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Juſtice</hi> are the great pillars of a Nation: when theſe ſtand f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rm and inviolate, then is a Nation hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. That the <hi>Church</hi> may floriſh in true Religion, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105057:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>State</hi> floriſh in the due Execution of Juſtice: this muſt be the deſire of our hearts, this we muſt endevour every one in his place, and this muſt every one pray for: <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to this purpoſe that the Apoſtle Paul ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhorts, <q>that ſupplications and prayers be made for Kings, and for all that are in Authority, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them we may live a quiet and peaceable life, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</q> The Kings and Emperors and Magiſtrates in thoſe times were Heathens and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of Chriſtian Religion yet the Apoſtle requires, that prayers and ſupplications be made for them. How much more ought we to pray for Chriſtian Kings and Princes, that under the Gracious Government of theſe <hi>Nurſing Fathers,</hi> Godlineſs and Honeſty, Religion and Juſtice may be nouriſhed and maintained: Good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to pray for Magiſtrats in the State, under whoſe protection we live, and by whome we enjoy peace and quietneſs.</p>
            <p>And we have good reaſon too, to pray for Miniſters in the Church. This the ſame Apoſtle requires: <hi>Pray for us.</hi> I deſire your prayers for me and my fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourors in the Goſpel: thoſe he means that are deſcribed there, that watch for your ſouls, and muſt give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for them; namely the Biſhops and Miniſters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Biſhops. They that have ſuch a great charge as the charge of Souls, that labour amongſt you in the word and doctrine, that exhort and admoniſh you in the Lord; they certainly may well exſpect the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and help of your prayers. Pray for us Miniſters in the Church, ſaith the Apoſtle, as well as for <hi>Magistrats</hi> in the State, that it may go well both with the Church and with the State.</p>
            <p>What the Apoſtle en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyns, that prayers ſhould be made for Magiſtrats and Miniſters, was duly remembred in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105057:4"/> compoſing and framing the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and publick prayers of the Church of England; as you may eaſily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, who are ſuch obedient ſons of the Church, as <hi>dayly</hi> to attend (which I do heartily wiſh, all, having no lawful hindrance, would do,) daily attend the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick divine Service. For example: <q>O Lord ſave the King, And, endue thy Miniſters with righteouſneſs. Againe for the King: O God, Behold our gracious Soveraigne Lord the King, and ſo repleniſh him with the grace of thy Holy Spirit, that he may alwayes encline to thy will and walke in thy wayes. And for the Miniſters: Send downe upon our Biſhops and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats the healthful Spirit of thy grace; and that they may truly pleaſe thee, pour upon them the continual dew of thy bleſſing.</q> Againe for the King: (By the way remember a Note of King Charls I of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; That ſure ſome of his Enemies were the more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended againſt the Common prayer book, becauſe it taught us to pray ſo much and ſo often for the King: a reaſon which may make thoſe who are loyal Subjects the more in love with it:) I ſay, Againe for the King, <q>So rule the heart of thy Choſen Servant, that he may above all things ſeek thy Honour and Glory: So rule his heart, that he may ſtudy to preſerve thy People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge in wealth, peace, and godlineſs. And yet againe, Save and defend our King, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him we may be Godly and quietly governed. Grant unto his whole Counſel, and to all that are put in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him, that they may truly and indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently miniſter Juſtice to the puniſhment of wickedneſs and vice, and to the maintenance of true Religion and Vertue.</q> Where alſo you may remember, it follows for the Church; <q>Give grace O Heavenly Father, to all Biſhops and Curates, that they may both by their life and Doctrine ſet forth thy true and lively Word, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105057:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> rightly and duly adminiſter thy Holy Sacraments.</q> Thus Beloved are we taught, in our divine Offices, to pray according to the Apoſtolical Ordinance, for the King and ſubordinate Magiſtrates, for the Biſhops and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Surely, Brethren, did we dayly and duly joyn, as we ought to do upon many Accounts, in our excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers, humbly and heartily: heartily I ſay (for we are many times, I fear, but cold and faint,) we ſhould, I doubt not in Gods good time, finde the ſucceſs of theſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited forces and <hi>aſſaults</hi> upon heaven (as Tertullian cals them) in the proſperity both of Church and State, as well as in the peace and comfort of our own Souls. But here's our miſery: ſome (whether through infirmitie of mind, or obſtinacy, God knowes,) will not come to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers: (they account them common in the worſt ſenſe, that is, <hi>Common and unclean:)</hi> ſome of us, when we are at Church, in the Houſe of God, mind not the Work of God, about which we come; behave not our ſelves as it becomes men that pray to the God of all Glory and Power; bring not with us that humility, that love, that faith, that zeale and fervor, that ſhould accompany, and quicken and ſeaſon our prayers. <hi>Aſke and you ſhall receive,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: but then we muſt aske aright with faith, and zeale, and love, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and (which is to be remembred, not only love to God, but Charity, ſweet and amiable Charity, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our neighbors, even to our enemies alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ask and receive not,</hi> ſaith S. James, <hi>becauſe ye aske amiſs.</hi> It is a common fault of People to murmur and complaine that Magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are not ſo good, Miniſters are not ſo good, as they ſhould be. But, may not we rather complaine of our ſelves and confeſs, We do not pray for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats, we do not not pray for Miniſters, as we ſhould pray. Verily, it were a courſe more becoming Chriſtians &amp; Godly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105057:5"/> men to turne our murmurings againſt Governors, into pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſupplications for them. For we may well beleive that by our continual prayers, our earneſt and ſincere p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayers, prayers proceeding from an humble and lowly, penitent and obedient Heart, that which is ſuppoſed to need a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, would be redreſſed, our Grievances eaſed; or at leaſt (which is a bleſſed fruit of true devotion,) our own ſouls would be better compoſed and fitted to bear all things without us, patiently and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to call to remembrance that which was known to ſome of us here preſent, how in the late times of trouble and confuſion, before the miraculous Return of his Majeſtie now Reigning (whom God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty long preſerve to reign in Truth and peace) in the time of the late troubles, how zealous, how conſtant, (notwithſtanding the danger of Aſſembling) were the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Miniſters and People (faithfull even then to our afflicted Mother the Church of England;) as if the fire of perſecution (as indeed it uſeth to do) had enflamed our devotions. We had a comfortable hope then; that ſhould we live to ſee the King againe in his Throne, the Biſhops in their Sees againe, and the Clergy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and the good laws and liberty reſtored to the languiſhing Church and people of God; we hoped and expected, that England would really become a Nation of Saints, an holy Nation, Chriſtians not in name only, but in deed and in truth. But alas! What happened? Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our Kings Returne, and with him the Returne of our Laws, and our Liberty, and our Religion, after the reeſtabliſhment of our Church and State, to the wonder and admiration of all the World, was not our ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, our unthankfulneſs no leſs wonderful? Did not the Devotions of many ſlacken and cool? Yea, did not Covetouſneſs and Ambition, did not licentiouſneſs and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105057:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> profanation, did not intemperance and exceſs, ſtrife and contention and faction, quickly ſpread themſelves over the Nation, and uſurp a new Dominion and reign over us? But to ſpeake moſt gently, did not even the better ſort fall much ſhort of that zeal for Gods honour and ſervice, that care of reformation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of Manners, both in our ſelves and others, which perhaps we once vowed, and certainely the Mercies, the unexſpected and undeſerved Mercies of God exacted at our hands?</p>
            <p>Surely, ſurely we were more ſtrongly obliged to be an holy People, a thankfull People, a praying Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; a People loving and Charitable, peaceable and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient; united in obedience to the State, and united in obedience to the Church: if not agreeing in all points of Doctrine and opinion (for there may be a mutual To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration in that reſpect,) yet however united in the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith</hi> of Chriſtians, and in the <hi>common Devotions</hi> and publick prayers, formed with great Wiſdom and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, agreeable to the common Faith. Where the fault of our Diviſions lyeth, God will Judge.</p>
            <p>But among our late Omiſſions ſince the Return, in Point of Solemn Aſſembling for Prayer and Thankſgiving, I cannot this Day forget to note the neglect formerly (I ſay not in this great City) generally in the leſſer Pariſhes of the Country; the neglect of obſerving this great Day. A great Day, juſtly ſo ſtiled, but greatly neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the greateſt part of the Nation. Was not this Neglect one ſin among many other, to provoke God to permit new Plots, more Popiſh Plots &amp; conſpiracies, to be contrived, &amp; fetcht out of the old Magazine of Hell 'againſt our merciful King and his loving People, againſt our Church and State, and all that is dear unto us. To theſe Traitors we ſhall ſay more anon: let us now go forward and ſpeak to our Text.</p>
            <p>This, this I feare, may be matter of juſt complaint that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105057:6"/> we were not thankful for our Peace and proſperity that returned with our King (whom God preſerve,) but we murmured at the management both of Church and State. For remedy whereof I ſhall mention but two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Holy Writ, which, as I conceive, being well conſidered may ſerve to abate and calm our murmuring. As to the affaires of State, is the burthen of Taxes and Tribute a Grievance? For this, take the Sentence of our Lord: <hi>Give unto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars.</hi> As to the Church, are Ornaments of our Mother, and her Ceremonies an eye ſore? For this Grief, take the good Aphoriſm of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be don de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in Order.</hi> Ceremonies in ſome meaſure (and you may ſee the meaſure, if you pleaſe to read the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces</hi> before the Liturgy,) ſome Ceremonies are neceſſary for the preſerving of that decency, which the Word of God and our own reaſon and common ſenſe requires: what Ceremonies are ſuch, our Governors muſt judge, not we. Tribute is neceſſary for the Defenſe of the King and Kingdome: what Tribute is ſuch, our Governors muſt judge, not we. They have the Power of <hi>Commanding:</hi> to us is left the praiſe of <hi>Obeying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe few words ſpoken of <hi>Tribute</hi> in the State and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in the Church, cannot ſeem impertinent or improper to my Text: For it may be obſerved, that the peace of our Jeruſalem hath been much impaired and is ſtill endangered, by ſuch as are apt, too apt to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at One or Both. The <hi>Seditious</hi> in the State, uſe to diſturbe the Civil Government, under pretence of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Impoſitions and taxes: The <hi>Sectaries</hi> in Religion love to untie the bonds of Eccleſiaſtical Politie under colour of ſuperſtitious Rites and Ceremonies: both ſorts are to be lookt upon, and lookt to, as enemies to the peace of our Jeruſalem. And you will excuſe your Teachers, and Spiritual Guids if they do <hi>Hoc agere,</hi> beſtow much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105057:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> care and paines in this behalf, that in this Noble City may be found no ſuch Sectaries, no ſuch ſeditious Perſons.</p>
            <p>Beloved, it is our hearts Deſire, and our prayer to God for you, that you may approve your ſelves, both obedient Subjects to the King (whome God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) and dutiful Sons of the church. And in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you will help to keep, help much (ſuch a City) to keep and preſerve and advance that which we pray for, the peace of our Jeruſalem. Our Obedience muſt under God, and the King, I ſay our <hi>Obedience</hi> muſt both procure and advance our peace. And without obedience unto Governors, our prayers for them ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy nothing, avail nothing. <hi>Pray</hi> for Governors; that's good: but then, we muſt <hi>obey</hi> them too. God is much pleaſed with the Obedience of his people; obedience to his own Laws and obedience to the Laws of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cegerents. Indeed the Laws of his Vicegerents are in a ſort Gods own Laws; ratified and eſtabliſhed by God. <hi>For by him Kings Reigne, and Princes decree Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tice.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to our Governors is obedience to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and to Chriſt our Lord. What Saint Paul faith of ſervants may be fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly applyed and accommodated to Subjects: <q>Subjects, be obedient to your King, doing the will of God from the heart (not in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew only, but from the heart) with good will ſhewing your obedience, as to the Lord and not unto men: knowing, that whatſoever good thing any man doth, the ſame ſhall be receive of the Lord.</q> Or, as it is elſewhere expreſſed by the ſame hand, Knowing, that of the Lord ye ſhall receive the Reward: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of your true and faithful Obedience.</p>
            <p>And this brings me to the <hi>Great Reaſon,</hi> or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Motive of our good Affection and good wiſhes to Jeruſalem in the latter part of the Text: <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee;</hi> that love and pray for thee O Jeruſalem.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105057:7"/>
            <p> II. <q>They that performe the Duty, that love the Church and State, and pray for the peace of them, procure proſperity and happineſs for themſelves.</q> For the declaration and proof of this, let us conſider firſt in general: That our prayers for others are always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to our ſelves. The Reaſon is, becauſe our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the performance of a Duty pleaſing unto God. It is pleaſing unto God, becauſe it is commanded by him. <hi>Pray one for another,</hi> ſaith Saint James. And omiſſion of this duty is a ſin, as appeares by the Words of Samuel: <hi>God forbid, that I ſhould ſin in ceaſing to pray for you.</hi> Now, if it be a ſin to deny another our prayers, if to pray for others be to performe a duty pleaſing to God and commanded by Him: hence it clearly follows, that it will be Profitable and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to us. For this is an infallible Truth: <hi>No man ever obeyed God in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Reaſon is, becauſe in our praying for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we exerciſe and encreaſe our brotherly kindneſs and Charity: And you know brotherly kindneſs and Charity is the great grace, the prince of Graces, commended unto us in the Goſpel of Chriſt: who hath taught it, by his example and precept, and hath ſet it down as the proper mark and character of his Diſciples. This love and charity, as it makes us prone to do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Offices for our Neighbours, ſo eſpecially does it incline us to pray for them. This is a Charitable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which the pooreſt may performe for the richeſt: an Office which we can perfome for our worſt enemies. When they ſtand at ſuch a diſtance from us, that we can do them no other good, we can, and muſt pray for them, according to the Command of our Lord and Maſter. And by the exerciſe of this Charity, we encreaſe it, and procure no ſmall benefit to our ſelves, as well as to them for whom we pray. Thus in generall.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105057:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Now let us in particular ſpeak of our love to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and our praying for Jeruſalem; that is, for our Church and State: and firſt for the State, or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government. What is the end and effect of our prayers for the <hi>State,</hi> for the King (whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) and all that are in Autority under him, no man can better tell us than Saint Paul: <hi>That we may lead a quiet and peacible life, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I. A quiet and and peacible life.</hi> Do you know what a bleſſing it is to lead a quiet and peacible life? If you do not value this bleſſing, look back upon the time, that is within our memory, the time of our late domeſtic Wars and tumults; when the late King, a juſt and merciful and religious Prince, was put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his Government firſt, weakened and deveſted of his Royal power and prerogative firſt; and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his life and all. Look upon the time of our preſent Sovereigns exile in forreign parts, what facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what changes and uncertainties of Government, what oppreſſion and cruelties, before his Majeſties hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Returne. There are but few among us ſo old, that can look back to the 5 of November 1605. Not to ſpeake of the terrible Invaſion in 88, in the time of the famous Queen Elizabeth: when the Spaniſh Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da (that Invincible Armada, as it was proudly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,) threatned utter ruine to this Kingdome, but was it ſelfe by Gods Aſſiſtance ruined and defeated: when that of Claudian was hanſomly applyed to the Queen; <hi>Onimium dilecta Deo, cui militat aether, Et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurati veniunt ad claſſica venti!</hi> But the year 1605, ſome few among Old men may remember, and moſt men are acquainted with the hiſtory of the gunpowder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: a Treaſon ploted by pretended Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>holicks, and for the pretended promotion of Chriſtian Religion: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, indeed and in truth, it was a plot moſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105057:8"/> to the doctrine of Chriſt, and tending to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of a Church, (of all other Churches we know,) whoſe Doctrine and Conſtitutions are moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the primitive Church of Chriſt, truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Apoſtolick. <q>It was a plot for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as the Records teſtify to all poſteritie,) for the deſtruction of the King, (that King of ſuch admirable learning and piety King James) the Queen, the Prince, and all the Royal branches, with the whole Clergy and Commons of this Realm, then aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; by popiſh treachery, appointed as ſheep to the ſlaughter, in a moſt barbarous and ſavage manner, beyond the examples of former Ages. An unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſpiracy (I ſpeake the words of Autority) an unnatural Conſpiracy:</q> An horrible and wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, plotted and intended this day (a diſmall day, if it had taken affect) againſt the King and the whole State; for the ſubverſion of the Government and the Religion eſtabliſht amongſt us.</p>
            <p>But it pleaſed God, in a ſtrange manner to diſcloſe the plot and lay open the ſecret deſigne, (as he hath given a ſtrange diſcovery of the late ſo much noiſed deſign, no leſs dangerous to our preſent King, than Church and State, yet in being and long to be by Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:) the <hi>Powder-Plot</hi> I ſay was marvellouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered: God gave the King to underſtand a dark and obſcure Letter, and by that the black deſign came to light; the conſpirators ſome taken, ſome ſlain in the purſuit, ſome Judged according to Law, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Executed, as was fit for Traytors. The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable and horrid effects and conſequences of which Treaſon, had not the hand of God been againſt them and for us, are beyond my ability to comprehend, much more beyond my expreſſion. 'Tis ſufficient, if you imagine and fancy ſo much of that confuſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105057:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> which would have followed, as to make us have a more lively ſenſe of the greatneſs of our deliverance, and the bleſſing of a quiet and a peaceable life, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I was ſpeaking: and withall make us to ſolemnize this Day of our deliverance with due Thankfulneſs, and with a ſober and Religious joy, together with bountiful Alms to the poor. I ſay againe, and would have it marked, <hi>with a ſober and Religious joy,</hi> leaſt in a ſinful and profane celebration (as the manner of ſome is) we provoke God to deliver us to ſome new Plotters and Conſpirators. And that there is a new plot of the papiſts in great part diſcovered, and in ſome part puniſhed already, I need not tell you. I do but touch this thereby to urge you not only to a Religious thankfulneſs <hi>this Day,</hi> but to a ſincere Amendment of life, and uniforme Obedience <hi>every Day,</hi> that the Sword of God hanging over our heads as it were by a ſlender thread, may be prevented and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Which I pray God, in mercy grant.</p>
            <p>In one of the prayers for this day, we deſire of God <q>to ſtrengthen the hands of our gracious King, and of all that are in Authority under Him, with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtice to cut of all ſuch workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, as <hi>turn Religion into Rebellion, and Faith into faction.</hi>
               </q> I remember we read it in the old Book for the <hi>Fifth of November</hi> about Forty years agon, thus: <q>Cut of all ſuch workers of iniquity, <hi>whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is Rebellion, and their Faith is Faction.</hi>
               </q> I doubt not, the alteration was made upon ſome reaſon, then. But more, ſince our Intelligence of the New Plot, (does it not ſtil proceed?) we may reſtore the Antient reading, and if ever it might be juſtly ſaid, it may now moſt deſervedly be pronounced of the Jeſuitical Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; <hi>Their Faith is Faction: Their Religion is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</hi> If any man doth yet de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y or doubt of This,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105057:9"/> he may ſatisfy himſelf abundantly in the late Book pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the moſt learned Biſhop of Lincoln, to omit many other.</p>
            <p>Since this new-old plot of the Jeſuits, the King the State and the Church have been judged to lie under ſo eminent danger, that doubts and fears have run through the whole Kingdom, but dwelt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in <hi>London,</hi> the famous London, the Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome or Compendium of the Kingdom. Before which time (I think I may ſay) in moſt of the ſpace ſince the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Return, Every man, that lov'd quiet, might ſit quietly and ſafely under his own vine and his own fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree (as the Hebrews ſpeak,) that is, every man enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own, and eat the labour of his hands ſecurely, Religion was ſafe, and the people without fear did or might pray and hear as their forefathers pray'd and heard in the peaceable reigns of Queen Elizabeth and King James, and in the beginning of King Charles the firſt; namely, hear the ſaving word read and preached by lawfully ordained prieſts; and pray the good old prayers; only with a new Reviſe ſince the happy Return, for our better ſatisfaction and edification. Many more benefits I might mention, but our liberty and our daily bread, and our true Religion, (would it might ſhine in the Uniformity of our lives and actions,) theſe may ſuffice to ſhew the great reaſon we have to pray for our Jeruſalem, for our Civil Government particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, free from plots and conſpiracies of our irreconcileable Enemies, free from diſcords, and diſſentions, of our own Brethren.</p>
            <p>But <hi>peace and quietneſs</hi> is then moſt valuable, when it is attended with that which follows, <hi>Godlineſs and Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty:</hi> The end and benefit of Government is, that we may lead a quiet and peacible life <hi>in all Godlineſs and honesty.</hi> Godlineſs and honeſty are well joined with peace
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105057:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and quietneſs: For publick tranquillity and ſafety is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot given us, that we ſhould abuſe it to rioting and drunkenneſs, to chambering and wantonneſs, to ſtrife and envying: <q>but that being delivered out of the hands of our enemies, and being without fear of them, we might fear God, and ſerve him in holineſs and righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all our days:</q> that is, behave our ſelves juſtly and mercifully toward our neighbours, devoutly and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently toward God: and this, with perſeverance to the end. Righteouſneſs and Holineſs muſt go hand in hand together: Godlineſs and Honeſty muſt not be parted.</p>
            <p>The good <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land are made as well to promote religion as Juſtice; and the commands of the King are to make his ſubjects Gods ſubjects, his people Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. We have laws, wholſome laws, as on the one hand to keep us from offending God by ſwearing and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo on the other to reſtrain us from offending the neighbour by railing, evil ſpeaking, and diffamation. Which particular I mention, becauſe we live in an Age wherein evil ſpeaking, and evil writing too, is brought into a faſhion by <hi>buſy-bodies,</hi> (or rather idle-bodies,) and made an exerciſe of Wit: which was given them, by the favour of God, for better uſes. Grave and learned men are ſometimes expoſed in their <hi>Lampoons,</hi> begotten (as they ſay) by Copulation of male and female Wits: but theſe <hi>brats</hi> are not fit to be nurſed up, or ſent abroad into the world by the hand of any ſober or civil perſon. Among the diſeaſes of our time, ſuch Scrible<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be call'd the ſcab and itch of the Age: and unleſs thoſe irregular and intemperate Wits be curbed by Authority, they may prove the very bane of humane ſociety and all good fellowſhip. In the mean time, for your Lampoons, Contempt is the beſt reveng, and we may ſay with Tacitus <hi>Spreta exoleſcunt.</hi> When good men are reviled either by unruly Tongues, or ſharper pens, they will think upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105057:10"/> the words of Chriſt, <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you:</hi> and think upon the example of Chriſt their Maſter; <hi>who when he was reviled, reviled not again.</hi> Good laws I ſaid, we have to keep us from diſhonoring God by ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prophanation, and to reſtrain us from offending the neighbour by ſlander and diffamation: Good Laws, if well executed. Therefore muſt we pray alſo, that the ſame God, who hath given us laws eſtabliſh't by Acts of Parliament, and commanded by royal proclamation, for the maintenance of Godlineſs and honeſty, would alſo be pleaſed, by his effectual Grace, to raiſe up the hearts and courage of <hi>Magistrates,</hi> both in this city and all other places, to maintain the laws, and ſee to their due execution.</p>
            <p>This is the way to have our peace and quietneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and continued to us by maintaining Godlineſs and honeſty. <hi>Godlineſs</hi> (which you muſt remember is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be joyned with honeſty: The Godly man is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an honeſt man:) <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> I ſay <hi>hath the promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come:</hi> ſo <hi>Saint Paul.</hi> Temporal promiſes, and ſpiritual promiſes: proſperity of all ſorts. For the ſoul alſo is ſaid to proſper: And the proſperity of the ſoul is, when it proceedeth from grace to grace, and is prepared more and more for Glory. This is the chiefeſt part of the proſperity of thoſe that love Jeruſalem, and pray for Jeruſalem. The proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the outward or temporal eſtate is, when you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your wordly buſineſs in your honeſt vocations with ſafety and good ſucceſs: and this is the reward of thoſe that love the State and Government. In ſeeking the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and welfare of the King, they ſeek the good of Gods kingdome: for, <hi>The King reigns for God:</hi> and they that ſeek Gods Kingdom, ſhall have all neceſſaries of this life added to them. We have our Saviours word for it. They ſhall be proſpered and bleſſed in their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105057:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> outward concerns, and all their temporal affairs.</p>
            <p>The mention of Gods kingdom, puts me in mind of the other part propoſed concerning the <hi>Church.</hi> I have ſhewed, how they procure a bleſſing for themſelves, that love and pray for the publick <hi>State</hi> or common wealth, or civil government; now let me briefly ſhew you the ſame in reſpect of the <hi>Church,</hi> or Ecleſiaſtical government: They that love the Church of God, and pray for the Church-men, do thereby procure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and happineſs for themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Church at large, that is, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, is the Congregation of Chriſtian people all the world over; but here we underſtand the ruling and unruling part of the Church, that is, the <hi>Biſhops and Miniſters</hi> under them; thoſe particularly of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> placed under his Majeſties ſupreme authority and government. And they that love the Church, are diſcerned by theſe two characters: They pray for the Biſhops and Miniſters, and obey their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and inſtruction. For this <hi>Obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t testimony of their love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, they that pray for the <hi>Biſhops and Minist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> procure to themſelves proſperity. 'Tis a great h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to the people of God, to have good Biſhops and Miniſters: and the way to have ſuch, is to pray for them. Theſe are call'd Labourers in Gods harveſt: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our Saviour hath ſaid, Pray the Lord of the harveſt, that he would ſend forth labourers into his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rveſt. The true labourers are of God's ſending: they do not intrude themſelves without a call, but are ſent by God in an orderly way. That you may have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch, you muſt pray for them; and when you have them, you muſt pray for the continuance of them, and for God's bleſſing on them in their labours. So ſhall that gracious promiſe of God be fulfilled among us, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> recorded by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105057:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the prophet Jeremy: I will give you Paſtors according to mine own heart, which ſhall feed you with knowledge and underſtanding: learned and godly Biſhops and Miniſters; ſuch as the Church of England <hi>(Dicam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante invidiâ)</hi> ſuch as our Church is bleſſed with in our Time, and hath been bleſſed with in the former Age. Theſe are a great happineſs to the people (if they would be pleaſed to know their own happineſs,) a great happineſs to the people of God. And this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs will be the better known, if you have the leaſure ſometimes to weigh the ſeveral parts of their office. They are to feed you (as the prophet ſaid) to feed you with knowledge and underſtanding: brighter and clearer knowledge, than that in the prophet's time: The knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified: The knowledge of him, and the power of his Reſurrection: They are to guide you in your doubts, to comfort you in your ſorrows: They are to call you off from the way of error, and the path that leadeth to deſtruction: and to ſhew you the right and good way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and to ſhew you what God would have you do, and what God will do for you, if you beleive in him and ſerve him; even bring you ſafe to everlaſting Glory. You may be glad to pray for ſuch perſons, and to love them, by whoſe miniſtry you obtain ſuch ineſtimable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and bleſſings.</p>
            <p>And we muſt not only pray for them, but obey them too, that our obedience may ſecure our proſperity. Obedience I ſay, is the beſt teſtimony of love, and it is the fruit of love. The Apoſtle preſſes the duty of obedience to Biſhops and Miniſters, by the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Souls committed to their charge. They that obey their ſpiritual Rulers, ſhall be improved in their ſouls, advantaged in their whole converſation. So that a comfortable <hi>Account</hi> ſhall be given of them to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105057:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> God the lover of ſouls. For what greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and joy can be both to Miniſters and people, than to live together in the fear of God, and in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual love here; and when God ſhall call them hence, to meet again in heaven, and be with Chriſt in perfect joy for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſerve for the proſperity of thoſe that pray for and love the State, and likewiſe of their proſperity that pray for and love the Church.</p>
            <p>And now to draw to a Concluſion, if you pleaſe to reflect upon the plain diſcourſe you have had the patience to hear, you may thence make a diſcovery of the <hi>friends and enemies</hi> either of Church or State.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We diſcern who are friends, and who enemies to the <hi>State.</hi> They that pray heartily for the State, for the King and all that are in Authority under the King: they that ſecond their prayers with a loving, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, humble and obedient behaviour, contributing to the publick what ſervice they can in their ſeveral ſtations. Theſe are the friends of the King, theſe are friends of the State, theſe the beſt Commonwealth-men, theſe the moſt loyal Subjects.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Chriſtians, in the primitive Times, the times of perſecution, were accuſed as enemies of the Roman Empire, and cauſes of all publick miſcheifs and calamities. To refute this ſlander, and defend the innocent profeſſors of Chriſtianity, Tertullian a man of a ſtrong wit and ſharp Eloquence, pleads thus: <q>
                  <hi>Oramus pro omnibus Imperatoribus &amp;c.</hi> We pray for all Princes, that it may pleaſe God to grant them long life, ſecure Goverment, a ſafe Family, valiant Armies, a faithful Counſel, a good people, quiet times, and whatſoever good things they themſelves can deſire, either as men or Princes.</q> Thus the primitive Chriſtians were wont to pray for the Princes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105057:12"/> and Magiſtrates, and by theſe prayers proved they were <hi>friends</hi> to the preſent State.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, that man that takes himſelf to be a royalliſt, a friend of the King, and a faithful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and only talkes, or drinks a health; and does not, both in publick and private, pray for the welfare of the King and Kingdom, is very much miſtaken. Can he truly love the King, that does not heartily pray for the King? The loving Subject, is the praying Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and he will not fail in any other act or duty of obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the diſcovery of the <hi>Churches</hi> freinds and enemies, you have heard, that by the Church is chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant the Ruling part, the Biſhops and Miniſters. So the word ſeemeth to be underſtood in that precept of Chriſt, <hi>Die Eccleſiae,</hi> Tell it to the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Rulers of the Aſſemblies, as our learned Paraphraſt has it out of Chryſoſtome. Theſe Rulers ſpirituall, if we do not pray for, we are no freinds, but enemies of the Church. For theſe are given by the ſpecial favour and providence of God; for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, as Saint Paul ſaith. They are given, as the ſame Apoſtle adds, <q>that being inſtructed and guided by them, we be no more children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</q> So then, if our ſettlement in the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and our preſervation from dangerous Errors; if our edification and growth and perfection depend under God upon the ſacred Miniſtry; certainely he, can be no freind to Religion and the Goſpel, who does not not love and pray for the Biſhops and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs it is true, and often found by ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that <hi>Church-men</hi> have many Enemies. And no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105057:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> wonder: For the Prophets of old, and after them the Apoſtles, yea Chriſt himſelfe our Lord and Maſter, had their Enemies, ſlanderers, revilers. Elias the Prophet was accuſed as a troubler of Iſrael: Paul the Apoſtle was accounted for a ſeditious fellow, and his own Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſeem to have been his Enemies for his <hi>telling them the truth.</hi> And is not this that, which raiſeth up en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt our preachers ſomtimes, even the telling them the Truth. The truth is, we love our ſins, and favour our own luſts and vanities, and would not be vehemently urged to part with any thing which is <hi>in deliciis,</hi> a delight to us, and dear as the right hand or eye. We care not to be taught, how to be grave, and yet withall kind; ſtrict and yet courteous, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and yet ſociable; as our Religion, our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity exacteth. We can hear the Doctrine, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure not to come under the Diſcipline of the church.</p>
            <p>And here among the Churches <hi>Enemies,</hi> I might fall againe upon the Popiſh Traytors, both old and new, the grand Adverſaries of our Jeruſalem, both of our Church and State. But 'tis time to eaſe you, and I had rather pray, then inveigh. Wherefore I intreat you to joyn with me in your moſt ardent deſires, that God would be pleaſed, ſtill to diſcover, and defeat, and blaſt his and our enemies: that our Soveraigne Lord the King may ſtill be protected by the Divine power, and directed by the Divine Wiſdom: that the Parliament now ſummoned, may in due time meet together, and ſit f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, with ſuch unanimity and concord in their Counſels, ſuch order and prudence and ſucceſs in their Affaires, that they may be a joy to the King, and to all his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubjects, and may riſe with the honour, the laſting honour, of having been the reeſtabliſhers of truth and peace for us and our poſterity.</p>
            <p>I muſt not end, till I have in a word admoniſhed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105057:13"/> you of ſome other Traytors, and theſe the worſt of all. For thoſe Traitors aforementioned, could only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Body, but theſe deſtroy the Soul, the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Soul: I mean theſe privy Conſpirators in our own boſomes, our carnal luſts, and unruly paſſions, and our preſumptuous Sins proceeding thence. I need not name them. Theſe muſt be ſearched out, mortified, extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and totally deſtroyed. A great Work, but poſſible by the Grace of Almighty God, and by the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: which we ſhall receive, if we pray for it, as we ought to do, with humility and fervency and conſtancy.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the cloſe of all, let me earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Worthy Citizens here, that this magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and beautifull <hi>Baſilica,</hi> the Houſe of God (the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your ancient Corporation,) and the ſolemn ſervice dayly miniſtred in this Colledge, may be more frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and attended by you. And withall, let me petition, that the daily Divine Service (at leaſt in the mornings) may be procured and maintained according to the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our good Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in every Pariſh Church in this City. Conſider of it (if you pleaſe) Right Worſhipfull and beloved Brethren. Bear with my zeal in this propoſal: If ever you will be zealous for publick and Common Prayer, Now is the time. Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary occaſions call for our extraordinary care and diligence. <hi>Verbum ſapienti.</hi> My laſt words ſhall be taken out of a Prayer appointed for <hi>this Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>O Lord! Let the Conſideration of thy Goodneſs work in us true Repentance, that Iniquity may not be our ruine: And increaſe in us more and more a lively faith, and fruitfull Love in all holy Obedience; that thou maist continue thy favour, with the Light of the Gospel to us and our posterity for evermore. And that for thy dear Sons ſake, Jeſus Christ our only Mediator and Advocate.</hi> Amen.</q>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105057:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
